<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-01T15:18:42+01:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Simone Ramello</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The friends we made along the way: pay-off versus process in mathematical communication</title><link href="/2023/07/25/payoff.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The friends we made along the way: pay-off versus process in mathematical communication" /><published>2023-07-25T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2023-07-25T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>/2023/07/25/payoff</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/07/25/payoff.html"><![CDATA[<p>It is not a mystery that communicating mathematics, and particularly theoretical mathematics, proves to be a wholly different beast from communicating the natural or medical sciences. Many strategies that are useful for other fields, like <em>don’t show formulas</em> or <em>don’t use jargon</em> struggle to apply to mathematics; surely, mathematics is about more than formulas or definitions, and yet those are a fundamental part of it, not just a device to understand reality but a foundational component. If we refuse to communicate in our language, what story are we telling? And yet, this is a source of great frustration for those who try to communicate mathematics – often, the gap seems impossible to fill, the public sitting at a distance that doesn’t even allow for a lecture, let alone the conversation that successful science communication should look like (God forbid we go back to the deficit model).</p>

<h2 id="pay-off-versus-process">Pay-off versus Process</h2>
<p>A week ago I have attended a talk during <a href="https://scipep.org/event/2023-conference/">SciPep 2023</a>, titled <em>Identity and Inspiration: What do we know about “basic” scientists?</em>. In it, Chris Volpe from <a href="https://sciencecounts.org">Science Counts</a> presented evidence from two surveys that were conducted in 2018 and 2021 in both the engaged public and the scientific community. Among many interesting questions, one stuck out as particularly useful for understanding certain phenomena in science communication, namely: What words would you use to describe how you feel about science?</p>

<p>The results show that, while the public strongly associates <em>Hope</em> (63%) with science, the scientists are rather divided, splitting almost evenly between <em>Hope</em> and <em>Joy</em>. One is bound to wonder why that is; clustering the results along some natural choices (political stances, for example) did not yield any insight, but a stark difference appeared when breaking down scientists along their fields of study. Namely, natural scientists – and mathematicians – seemed to aggregate firmly in the <em>Joy</em> area, while engineers and social scientists stayed in the <em>Hope</em> area.</p>

<p>The conjectured explanation for this is a difference between a <em>payoff-minded</em> scientist, and a <em>process-minded</em> scientist. Scientific research is not a linear process, and in no field of scientific inquiry can one hope to input X effort and obtain Y = Y(X) output. The scientific process is inherently a jump of faith, no matter what the subject of study is. The difference between the <em>Joy</em> scientists and the <em>Hope</em> scientists, then, cannot be found in whether their research areas allow for optimism or not; on the other hand, it ought to depend on the attitute that those scientists have towards their work. Particularly, scientists conducting basic research associate <em>Joy</em> with their activities because they genuinely enjoy the process – they are, thus, more <em>process-minded</em>. On the other hand, scientists conducting applied research are more motivated by the outcome of their work and the impact it has on society, and are thus more <em>payoff-minded</em>. By contrast, the engaged public is almost entirely payoff-minded.</p>

<h2 id="a-voice-from-the-audience-why-should-we-care">A voice from the audience: Why should <em>we</em> care?</h2>
<p>Where does this leave mathematicians? The category sits neatly in the <em>process</em> area of Science Counts’ <a href="https://sciencecounts.org/wp-content/uploads/2019/07/Assessing-Scientist-Willingness-to-Engage-in-Science-Communication_web.pdf">report</a> (although, interestingly, below physicists). The frustration many mathematicians voice is echoed in the staggering distance from the public in their graphs; while many, if not most, mathematicians seem to be motivated by the process itself, finding joy and excitement in doing mathematics <em>for its own sake</em>, the public expects – if not an outright benefit for society – at least some output that can be understood, and enjoyed, by them as well.</p>

<p>In this regard – and in many others – mathematics is no different from narrative. Certain genres of fiction speak to some, but not to others; some stories resonate with certain people, but not with everyone. No book connects to the universal experience of being human; each presents a fragment, a perspective of reality, a point of view. And so does mathematics.</p>

<p>Why don’t we take a step back, then, and wonder <em>what</em> we want people to take home from mathematics? Do we want them to learn a definition, a theorem, an example? Or do we, perhaps, want them to connect to mathematics as a human pursuit, as a way to understand ourselves and reality? Sure, most of us do mathematics because it is fun, we find it interesting and stimulating; but we have not been blessed by some higher god with an innate connection to the subject. <em>Why</em> do we like doing mathematics? Did we connect with it because of a certain teacher, who showed us respect and uplifted us until we got to terms with the difficulties of its language? Didn’t we, once, also struggle with the apparent impenetrability of mathematical jargon?</p>

<p>When we read a book, we don’t expect it to provide us with immediate tools to deal with concrete problems. Why do we try so desperately to find applications of mathematics, when we prepare to speak to the general public?
When we immerse ourselves into a story, into some characters, walk in somebody else’s shoes and see with somebody else’s eyes, we don’t do it because we are sure that it will provide insight into <em>our</em> lives, into our thoughts, into our mental processes. And yet, in the end, it always does, even we don’t expect it. We, then, have to tell our mathematical stories as we see them, as they excite us, acknowledging that those we are in conversation with might have had a different path in life, and thus cannot resonate with the subject as we do.</p>

<p>This is not just a matter of <em>our</em> attitudes, as mathematicians; it is also a matter of how society portrays mathematics and mathematicians, which are not something <em>other</em>, but are members of society themselves, with their lived experiences, their moments of weakness, their personal interpretation of what <em>humanity</em> means. It is a human story that deserves to be told, and might resonate with some, or might not. Mathematics, for many of us, is a way to understand ourselves and the world around us, like for some it is poetry, or fiction, or art. It is a cultural product and as such, it should be understood as a game humans play to make sense of their reality – sometimes, just like it happens with fiction, providing us with tools to <em>concretely</em> deal with it. To fill the gap between the two sides of this conversation we so desperately hope to establish, we need to put back <em>humanity</em> in mathematics, through our feelings, our downfalls, our stories, which are – like characters in a novel – inextricably tied with our research and our work.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It is not a mystery that communicating mathematics, and particularly theoretical mathematics, proves to be a wholly different beast from communicating the natural or medical sciences. Many strategies that are useful for other fields, like don’t show formulas or don’t use jargon struggle to apply to mathematics; surely, mathematics is about more than formulas or definitions, and yet those are a fundamental part of it, not just a device to understand reality but a foundational component. If we refuse to communicate in our language, what story are we telling? And yet, this is a source of great frustration for those who try to communicate mathematics – often, the gap seems impossible to fill, the public sitting at a distance that doesn’t even allow for a lecture, let alone the conversation that successful science communication should look like (God forbid we go back to the deficit model).]]></summary></entry></feed>